<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Een nieuu tiidinghe hoe dat die Prince van Spaegien triumphelick aengecomen is in Enghelandt, mist gaders die bruyloft to Winchestre ghehouden.</title>
            <author>Philip II, King of Spain, 1527-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1554</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19835</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848105</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09556)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1638:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Een nieuu tiidinghe hoe dat die Prince van Spaegien triumphelick aengecomen is in Enghelandt, mist gaders die bruyloft to Winchestre ghehouden.</title>
                  <author>Philip II, King of Spain, 1527-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed abroad :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1554]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Not an STC item--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="dut">dut</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="dut">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13183:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 130 -->
            <p>Een nieuu tii<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinghe / hoe dat die Prince van Spaengien triumphelick aenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comen is in Enghelandt / miſiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders die bruyloft te Winche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtre ghehouden.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon of Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor</figDesc>
                  <head>PLVS OVLTRE</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13183:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 131 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:13183:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 131 -->
            <head>¶ Extract wt eenen brief gheſcre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen ende gheſouden wt Londen den leſten dach Iulij.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eminde vrient ghy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſult weten / dat ick ghecome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aldaer die gantſche vlote der <abbr>ſchep</abbr> des Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce van Spaengien aenghecomen is. Tſchip daer in dat die Prince ouer qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / was wtnemende ſchoo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> binnen ende buyten met root da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſt behanghen / ende met root flouweel ghebordeert. Daer wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren op meer dan tſeuentich meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len ſtucken / ende bouen dry hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dert ende vijftich mannen. Ick verſtae dat int tſelue ſchip meer dan twee millioene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ware<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gout
<pb facs="tcp:13183:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->
ende ſiluer / alleen van Sprincen weghe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſonder tgene dat andere ſcepen noch ghebracht hebben / he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ende andere groote heeren noch toebehoore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Ick en hebbe miin daeghe noyt ſchoonder vlote van ſchepen gheſien ſoo wel gheruſt ende gheequipeert. Daer is een groot volck ouercomen met wijl ende kinderen / ontrent ſes hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dert Spaenſche peerde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ende vijf duyſent knechten. Maer die en co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men noch niet aen lant / voor dat die Keyſerlijcke Maieſteyt ordon neert waer dat crijchs volck he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen ſal. Deſe vlote was wel van hondert en twintich ſchepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / daer onder dat ſommighe waren van vier meerſen / Maer des Princen ſchip was van vijf meerſſen. Die
<pb facs="tcp:13183:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->
plonderinghe ende des goets is ſoo veel / datter vijfthien hondert waghenen toe beſtelt zijn om dat te voeren / daer ziin oock veel prie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters ende ſommighe religieuſen. Ende onder ander twee Monic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken / diemen ſeydt des Princen Biechtuaders te zijn. Den ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghenthienſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dach Iulij / was die Prince aen landt ghecome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Den ſeluen dach is oock eene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeer groo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten ſtorm in die zee gheweeſt van reghen ende do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cker weder. Den ſeluen dach heeft die Prince noch thien mijlen willen trecken nae Wincheſtre. Al daer is hy gheco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drijent wintichſten Iulij / tſauonts met alle ſiin heeren ende der Coninghinnen heeren / ſo dat ter meer dan twee duyſent peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:13183:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
ware<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ende alle herberghen ſoo vol / dat wi ouſe peerden moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten ſes Engelſche mijlen weder om te rugghe ſeynden. Dat cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raet van ſchoone leedere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> op bey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſijden en coſt niet ſuffiſantelick weders wille. Want als hy te An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thona wt reedt om te Wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheſtre te comen / ſoo ſtont daer ſulcken weder op ghelijck doen hi Thant werpen ſijn entree dede. Als hy ce Winceſtre quam / ſoo reedt hy eerſt nae die kercke. Al daer was eenen outaer voor de kerck duere ghemaeckt / en<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daer op lach eenen boeck ende een cruys om dat hy dat ſelne cuſſen ſoude. Alle die Biſſchoppen ſtonden daer ende ontfinghen hem. Sijn cleet was eenen ſwerten flouwele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pall rock
<pb facs="tcp:13183:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
al met peerlen ghebordeert. Die Coninghinne ſandt hem teghen tweelf Enghelſche tellenaers.</p>
            <p>Hy ſadt op eenen witten / die tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wanten oft archiers waren al meeſt Enghelſche. Den gantſen raet van die Coninghinne ſate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> af gaende voor hem. Ende die Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce allee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was te peerde / Als hynv (als vore gheſeyt is) voor die kerc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke quam / ſoo ſadt hy af voor den out aer ende cuite dat cruys. Doe werdt hy vander geeſtelijckheyt gheleydet in die kercke: Ende de dore achter hem toe gheſloten: en de van daer wert hy in ſijn loghs ghebracht.</p>
            <p>De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vierent wintichſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dach der voerſcreuer maent Iulij nae mid dach is hy tot der Coninghinnen
<pb facs="tcp:13183:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 134 -->
ghegaen / die welcke hem teghen ghinck met alle die vrouwen en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ionckfrouwen / die welcke hy ontfinck ſoo dat betaemde / ende omheldeſe: doe leuerde ſi hem dz ſweert ouer / dwelck die Millord Tarby voer haer droech. En<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> als hitſelue inde hant ghenomen had<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / ſoo werdet den voerſcreuene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tarby weder ghegheuen.</p>
            <p>Doen na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hi die Coninginne by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hant / ende quamen in die pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentz camer (die alſoo gheheeten is) met alle die vrouwen ende io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c frouwen / ende Spaenſche heere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ende oock Engelſche. Al daer ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den twee ſetelen vergult met ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen gulden hemel bouen ſeer ſcoo ne / daer onder hebben ſy beyde een half vre alleen int aenſien van
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13183:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 134 -->
bijſtaende perſoonen met malcan de ren gheſproecken. Nae deſen ſoo is die Prinche ghegae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tot die vergaderinghe van dandere vrou wen ende ioncfrouwen die apart ſtonden / ende ſpracſe aen. Binne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſen middelen tijde heeft die Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninginne alle die Spaenſche hee ren haer hant laten cuſſen. Ende le duc Dalba die ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t neffens die Coninginne / haer te kennen ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uende wie elck heere was die tot haer quam. Ick en ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t niet twee ſcreden daer af / ſoo dat ickt al wel coſt ſien. Als die Prince niet ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heel twee vren by haer gheweeſt hadde / ſoo is hy weder in ſijn pal leys ghegaen. Sijn cleedinghe was eenen ſwarten flouweelen rock / oock met peerlen ende edel
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13183:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 135 -->
ghebordeert. Deſghelijcx ſijn cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe / ende witte couſſen / hebbende ae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſijn flinck bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die orde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / te wete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die iartiers oft gordel met iuwee len ende peerlen / den welcke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die Coninghinne hem teghen gheſon den hadde. Den vijuent wintich ſten dach Ium / op ſint Iacops dach / ſoo ſijn ſi ter kercken ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaen in gants gulden ſtucken / al daer ee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> groote ſtellagi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e oft ſolder opghericht was. Die Biſſchop van Wincheſt re met allen ſijnen aenhanck ghingen hem teghen. die welcke nae dat hy een groot lanck ſermoon in Enghels ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daen hadde / ſoo gafhijle te ſamen ende van op die ſtellagie wert ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proclameert den titel van deſen Prinche / ende die Coninghinne
<pb facs="tcp:13183:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 135 -->
nae tennere ſoo als hier na volget</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Philippus ende Marie / van Godts ghenaden Coninck ende Coninghinne van Enghelant / Vranckrijck / Napels / Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ende Irla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / beſchermers des gheloofs / Prince ende Princerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe van Spaengien / Cicilie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Eertſ hertoghen van Ooſtenriick / Her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toghen van Melanen / Bourgoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnen ende Brabant / Graue va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Habſburg / Vlaenderen ende Tirol.</head>
               <p>ENde als ſi afghegaen wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren / ſoo nam die Prinche haer byder luchter hant ende ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſe inden choor voor den groote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> outaer / daer knielden ſi te ſamen ende boorde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daer die hooghe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:13183:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 136 -->
met alle die vergadering he va die vrouwen ende groote heeren ſchier een vre lancduerende. Van daer ghinck yeghelick nae ſiin lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus. Ende in een ſeer groote ſale op een verhenen plaetſe daer op dat twee hondert perſoonen ſtae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moghen / is den Prince ende der Coninghinnen bereyt gheweeſt een langhe tafel londer een gulde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtuck / ende twee vergulde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeteis Int afdaelen beneden ſo ſtonden vier langhe tafelen / daer aen ſadt des Prince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> volck / en<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die vrouwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ende ionckfrouwen. Die Prince ende die Coninginne ſijn mz mal tanderen ter tafelen gheſeten / en<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hun beyden werdt voor gheſnede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> van eenen Enghelſchen Heere ge naempt Millord Firarter / die
<pb facs="tcp:13183:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 136 -->
welcke vander Coninghinne nae Spaengien gheſonden was / en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de met den Prince weder ouer ge comen was. Millord Bembruck hiel den Prince / en<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Millord Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hielt <abbr>d</abbr> Coninginne dat ſweert voor die tafel ſoo langhe als ſy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: maer va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spaengiaert wort hy ghedient die hem alleen te drincken gaf. Die biſſchop van Wincheſtre ſadt alleen beneden aen des Princen tafel. Als die maeltijt inghenomen was / heeft hy ſyn bonette op ſiin hooft ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadt. Die Prince ende die Conin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginne brochte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hem / alſoo dat hy die meeſt gheeſtimeerde is. Den co<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wert hem oock van hem bey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den afgeſonden / alſoo als die Spaenſche heeren ende Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaden
<pb facs="tcp:13183:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 137 -->
al daer gheſete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waren / zijn ſy tot den Prinche opghegaen / le duc Dalba ten eerſten / daer nae ſijn die Ambaſſadeurs deen voor dander nae gheſtaen. Dambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur des Conincx van Vra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>crijck is hier te Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den ghebleuen / wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hy en waſſer niet ten beſten gheſie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Die duc Dalba ſoe ic <abbr>vſtae</abbr> / is mz zijn huyſurou ouercomen. Men ſeyt hy ſal nae Napels trecke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> om al daer Viceroy te zijn. Die groo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te heeren die met den Prince ouer ghecomen ſijn verthoonden he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> op die bruyloft met ſeer coſtelijcke cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deren. Deſghelijcx haer dienaers met ſoo wtnemende leuereyn dat bi mans ghedincken ſulcx nz ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſien en is. Godt gheue dat alle din<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghen met payſe en<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vrede vergaen moet. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:13183:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 137 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
